Register of the Xenia Joukoff Eudin Papers, ca. 1930-1970
Hoover Institution Archives
Xenia Joukoff Eudin Papers,
ca. 1930-1970
84026
Eudin, Xenia Joukoff
43 manuscript boxes, 5 card file boxes (20.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Writings, translations, notes, and clippings, relating to the Russian Revolution and to various aspects of Soviet society in the 1920s and 1930s, including politics, foreign policy, economics, agriculture, and minority policies.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1984.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Soviet Union; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921; Soviet Union--History--1917-1936
Biographical Note
Born, Poltava, Russia
1932-l968 Research associate at the Hoover Institution, Stanford University
1936 Became U.S. citizen
1939 Co-editor, Features and Figures of the Past: Government Opinion in the Reign of Nicholas II, by V.I. Gurko, Stanford University Press
1946 Co-editor, The Life of a Chemist, Memoirs of V. N. Ipatieff, Stanford University Press
1957 Co-author, Soviet Russia and the East, l920-l927, A Documentary Survey, Stanford University Press Co-author, Soviet Russia and the West, l920-l927, A Documentary Survey, Stanford University Press
1963 Co-author, M. N. Roy's Mission in China: The Communist-Kuomintang Split in l972, University of California Press
1966-67 Co-author, Soviet Foreign Policy, l928-l934, Volumes I and II, Hoover Institution Publications and Pennsylvania State University Press
1983 Died
Series Description
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1949-1978. (Box 1)
  Correspondence arranged alpha-betically by last name of correspondent.
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS. (Boxes 2-41)
  Drafts, notes, manuscripts and other research materials relating to X. Eudin's writing endeavors arranged alphabetically by title or by subject.
- SUBJECT FILE, 1919-1970. (Boxes 42-43)
  Printed matter, reprints, photo-copies and other materials, collected by X. Eudin, arranged alphabetically by author or subject.
- CARD FILE. (Boxes 44-48)
  Index cards listing sources used in research and writings.
Container List
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1949-1978
  - Adloff, Richard, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Allen, Gary, 1969 (Folder 2)
  - American Council of Learned Societies, 1977 (Folder 3)
  - Atkinson, Dorothy, 1968 (Folder 4)
  - Avrich, Paul, 1968, 1971 (Folder 5)
  - Bell, Jess, 1956, 1964, 1977 (Folder 6)
  - Bolloten, Burnett, 1963 (Folder 7)
  - Buber, Margaret, 1962 (Folder 8)
  - Burress, Richard T., 1977 (Folder 9)
  - Burton, R. A., 1954 (Folder 10)
  - Caswell, John E., 1953 (Folder 11)
  - Catell, Nancy, 1954 (Folder 12)
  - Dallin, Alexander, 1978 (Folder 13)
  - Drachkovitch, Milorad M., 1975-77 (Folder 14)
  - Emmons, Terence, 1968 (Folder 15)
  - Fairbank, John K., 1958 (Folder 16)
  - Fisher, Harold H., 1958, 1963 (Folder 17)
  - Fisher, Raymond H., 1955 (Folder 18)
  - Footman, David, 1959 (Folder 19)
  - Ford Foundation, n.d. (Folder 20)
  - Harrison, Kathryn, 1963 (Folder 21)
  - Hurley, Emmet D., 1969 (Folder 22)
  - James Irvine Foundation, 1958 (Folder 23)
  - Johnsson, S. H., 1975-78 (Folder 24)
  - Kennan, George, 1976-78 (Folder 25)
  - Kennan Institute for Advanced Russian Studies, 1976 (Folder 26)
  - Knoll, Samson B., 1978 (Folder 27)
  - Lane, Richard, 1977 (Folder 28)
  - Langer, Paul F., 1953 (Folder 29)
  - Leggett, George H., 1967 (Folder 31)
  - Lilienthal, Philip E., 1976 (Folder 32)
  - Lyons, Eugene, 1962 (Folder 33)
  - Mandel, Benjamin, n.d. (Folder 34)
  - Max C. Fleischmann Foundation of Nevada, 1958 (Folder 35)
  - Meijer, J., 1954 (Folder 36)
  - Mosely, Philip M., 1954, 1958, 1960 (Folder 37)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1977 (Folder 38)
  - North, Robert, 1976 (Folder 39)
  - Possony, S., 1962 (Folder 41)
  - Radkey, Oliver H., 1957-58, 1964 (Folder 42)
  - Rhinelander, Philip E., 1959-1960 (Folder 43)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 196l (Folder 44)
  - Rothwell, Easton, 1955, 1958 (Folder 45)
  - Scalapino, Robert A., 1959 (Folder 46)
  - Simmons, Ernest J., 1949 (Folder 47)
  - Slavic Review, 1962 (Folder 48)
  - Slusser, Robert M., 1964, 1977 (Folder 49)
  - Smith, Thomas C., 196l (Folder 51)
  - Sorich, Richard, 1953-54 (Folder 52)
  - Stanford University Press, 1959-1960 (Folder 53)
  - Sterling, J. E. Wallace, 1954-1976 (Folder 54)
  - Sworakowski, Witold S., 1957 (Folder 55)
  - Thornton, Richard, 1964 (Folder 56)
  - Triska, Jan F., 1958, 196l (Folder 57)
  - Weissman, Benjamin M., 1966 (Folder 58)
  - White, John A., 1960 (Folder 59)
  - Young, Hobart N., 1960 (Folder 61)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 62)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS
  - "Anti-Bolshevik Conflict in Northwest Russia, 1919-1920"
    - General (Box 2, Folder 1-5)
    - "The Allies and Northwestern Government, 1919" (Folder 6-7)
    - "American Relief Administration in the Baltics, 1919" (Folder 8-9)
    - "Bermondt-Avalov's Affairs in the Baltic States, 1919" (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - "Bolshevik Expectations After Germany's Defeat, 1918" (Folder 2-3)
    - "Estonia Under Soviet Rule, 1919" (Folder 4)
    - "Estonian Independence" (Folder 5)
    - "Finnish Aid to the Northwestern Army" (Folder 6)
    - "Finnish Independence" (Folder 7)
    - "Germany in the Baltic States Before Its Defeat in October 1918" (Folder 8)
    - "Germany in the Baltic States Before Its Defeat in October 1918" (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - "Kolchak and His Ministers" (Folder 2-3)
    - "Latvia Under Soviet Rule, 1919" (Folder 4-5)
    - "Northwestern Army, formation of" (Folder 6)
    - "Northwestern Army Reaches Petrograd, October/ November 1919" (Folder 7)
    - "Peace Between the Baltic States and RSFSR, 1919-1920" (Folder 8)
    - "Petrograd, Attacks on, 1919" (Folder 9)
  - Bibliographies (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Biographies (Folder 2)
  - Bolshevik Party (Folder 3)
  - "Bolshevik Struggle Against Internal Opposition: Cheka in Action, 1918-1921"
    - General (Folder 4-8)
    - General (Box 6, Folder 1-8)
    - General (Box 7, Folder 1-5)
    - "Murder of Imperial Family and Other Romanovs" (Folder 6)
    - "Public and Non-Bolshevik Parties" (Folder 7)
    - "Red Terror, 1918-1921" (Folder 8)
  - "Bolsheviks and Peasants, 1918-1921"
    - General (Box 8, Folder 1-7)
    - General (Box 9, Folder 1-7)
    - General (Box 10, Folder 1-7)
    - General (Box 11, Folder 1-7)
    - General (Box 12, Folder 1-9)
    - General (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
    - "Communist Propaganda in the Countryside, 1919-1920" (Folder 3)
    - "The Little Known War Between the Bolsheviks and the Peasants, 1917-192l" (Folder 4)
    - "Peasant Uprisings in Russia and Siberia, 1920-21" (Folder 5-7)
    - "Soviet Food Policy" (Folder 8-10)
    - "Soviet Food Policy" (Box 14, Folder 1-2)
    - "Unified Economic Plan, 1920-21" (Folder 3)
    - "War Communism, 1918-19" (Folder 4)
  - "Bolsheviks Efforts to Disintegrate the Russian Imperial Army: Creation of a New Army (Red Army)"
    - General (Folder 5-8)
    - General (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - "The Use of Other Nationals, 1918-1921" (Folder 2)
  - Caucasus (Folder 3)
  - China (Folder 4-5)
  - Civil War in Russia, 1918-1921 (Folder 6-7)
  - Civil War in Russia, 1918-1921 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Civil War in Siberia (Folder 2)
  - "Civil War in South Russia, 1918-1921"
    - General (Folder 3-8)
    - General (Box 17, Folder 1-6)
    - "Allied Intervention, 1918-19" (Box 18, Folder 1-7)
    - "Allied Intervention, 1918-19" (Box 19, Folder 1-8)
    - "Allied Intervention, 1918-19" (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - "Denikin's Complications With Various Population Groups" (Folder 2)
    - "Don Cossacks and the Red Army, 1918-19" (Folder 3-5)
    - "Final Retreat of the White Army, 1920" (Folder 6)
    - "The Ukraine During German Military Occupation" (Folder 7)
    - "The Ukraine During German Military Occupation" (Box 21, Folder 1-6)
    - "The Ukraine During German Military Occupation" (Box 22, Folder 1-6)
    - "The Ukraine During German Military Occupation" (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - "The Voluntary Army, 1919" (Folder 2-4)
    - "Wrangel's Last Stand in Crimea, 1920" (Folder 5-6)
  - Comintern (Folder 7)
  - Comintern and Asia (Folder 8)
  - Comintern and China (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Comintern front organizations, 192l- 1962 (Folder 2-7)
  - Comintern front organizations, 1921-1962 (Box 25, Folder 1-5)
  - "The Communist Impact on International Thought: The Communist Front as a Mechanism for Controlling World Opinion, 1921-1961: Documents and Materials," with Stephen Johnsson, n.d. (Folder 6)
  - "The Communist Impact on International Thought in the 20th Century"
    - "Communism and the Intellectuals, 1918-1962"
      - General (Box 26, Folder 1-3)
      - "Association of Friends of Soviet Russia" (Folder 4-7)
      - "International Association of Revolutionary Writers" (Folder 8)
      - "International Association of Revolutionary Writers" (Box 27, Folder 1)
      - "Post World War II Youth and Student Move- ment" (Folder 2-4)
      - "World Federation of Democratic Youth" (Folder 5-6)
    - "The Communist Struggle for Colonial and Dependent Peoples, 1920-1963"
      - "Baku Congress, 1920" (Folder 7)
      - "Communist Plans for the Peoples of Asia" (Folder 8-9)
      - "Communists on the Negro Question" (Folder 10)
      - "The League Against Imperialism" (Folder 11)
      - "The League Against Imperialism" (Box 28, Folder 1-3)
      - "Post World War II Afro-Asian Movement" (Folder 4)
    - "The Communists Wage Revolutionary War and Peace, 1918-1963"
      - General (Folder 5-7)
      - General (Box 29, Folder 1-2)
      - "Anti-Fascist and Anti-War Congresses, 1932" (Folder 3)
      - "Communist 'Peace' Offensive After World War II" (Folder 4-5)
      - "Communist Peace Propaganda, 1922-1939" (Folder 6-8)
      - "Germany's Defeat" (Box 30, Folder 1-2)
      - "International Congress of Peace, Brussels, 1936" (Folder 3)
  - Compulsory universal labor (Folder 4)
  - Far Eastern Republic (Folder 5)
  - Georgia, 1918-1920 (Folder 6-7)
  - India (Folder 8)
  - "Indoctrination of the Masses" (Folder 9)
  - International front organizations after World War II (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Lenin, references to (Folder 2)
  - "M. N. Roy and the Theory of Decolonization," with Robert North, April 1959 (Folder 3)
  - "M. N. Roy's Mission to China," with Robert North, n.d. (Folder 4)
  - Mongolia (Folder 5)
  - "Moscow's Views of American Imperialism," reprint, The Russian Review (Folder 6)
  - Nationality question (Folder 7)
  - Pan Pacific Trade Union (Folder 8)
  - Persian-Soviet relations, 1918-1920 (Folder 9)
  - Polish-Soviet relations, 1918-1920 (Folder 10)
  - Polish-Soviet relations, 1918-1920 (Box 32, Folder 1-3)
  - Polish-Soviet War, 1920-2l (Folder 4-6)
  - Proposed projects, outlines (Folder 7)
  - Reviews of articles and publications (Folder 8)
  - Reviews of articles and publications (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - Russia's advance into Asia (Folder 2)
  - Soviet foreign policy, 1934-35 (Folder 3)
  - "Soviet National Minority Policies," article, The Slavonic and East European Review, Vol. XXI, 1943 (Folder 4-5)
  - Soviet Russia and the East, 1920-1927 (Folder 6-8)
  - Soviet Russia and the East, 1920-1927 (Box 34, Folder 1-6)
  - Soviet Turkestan, 1918-1920 (Folder 7-8)
  - Stalin on the peasant problem during the collectivization period (Folder 9)
  - Turkestan (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous drafts and notes (Folder 2-7)
  - Miscellaneous drafts and notes (Box 36, Folder 1-8)
  - Miscellaneous drafts and notes (Box 37, Folder 1-7)
  - Miscellaneous drafts and notes (Box 38, Folder 1-7)
  - Miscellaneous drafts and notes (Box 39, Folder 1-7)
  - Miscellaneous drafts and notes (Box 40, Folder 1-6)
  - Miscellaneous drafts and notes (Box 41, Folder 1-7)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1919-1970
  - Alexinsky, Gregory, "The March on Petrograd," 1919-1920" (Box 42, Folder 1)
  - Balinov, "On the Origin of the Cossacks," n.d. (Folder 2)
  - Blumenthal, Irene, "The Peasants International and the Communist Peasant Movement," ca. 1950s (Folder 3)
  - Chinese Eastern Railway (Folder 4)
  - Daniels, Robert V., "The Kronstadt Revolt of 192l," reprint, The American Slavic and East European Review, Vol. X, December 1951 (Folder 5)
  - Dubois Clubs (Folder 6)
  - Hurley, Emmet D., "Evolution of the Soviet Bloc Since the Twentieth Party Congress," June 1968 (Folder 7)
  - Kaganovich, A. M., Kak Postroena VKP (b) (How the VKP (b) is Organized), Moscow, 1927 (Folder 8)
  - Karca, Ramazan, "The Soviet Propaganda in the East," 1959 (Folder 9)
  - Kristof, Ladis K., "The Russian Image of Russia: An Applied Study in Geopolitical Methodology," 1968 (Folder 10)
  - Moscow, history (Folder 11)
  - North, Robert, "Soviet and Chinese Goal Values: A Study in Communism as a Behavior System," n.d. (Folder 12)
  - Pipes, Richard, "The First Experiment in Soviet National Policy - The Bashkir Republic, 1917-1920," reprint, The Russian Review, October 1950 (Folder 13)
  - Platonov, S. F., The Time of Troubles, 1970 (Folder 14)
  - Riasonovsky, Nicholas V.
    - "The Emergence of Eurasianism," reprint Califor- nia Slavic Studies, Vol. IV, 1967 (Folder 15)
    - "Russia and Asia: Two Nineteenth-Century Russian Views," reprint, California Slavic Studies, Vol. I, 1960 (Folder 16)
  - Rickman, Lydia Lewis, "Random Impressions of Russia Forty Years After," 1958 (Folder 17)
  - Sorkin, G. Z.
    - "Antiimperialisticheskaia Liga (Anti- Imperialist League), 1927-1935," Moscow, 1965 (Folder 18)
    - "Pervyi S'ezd Narodov Vostoka" (First Conference of the Peoples of the East), Moscow, 196l (Folder 19)
  - "Studying the 'Tatar Influence': Notes for a Methodology," n.d. (Folder 20)
  - Tschebotarioff, Gregory P., "The Captive Nations," February 1962 (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - Vernadsky, George, Medieval Russian Laws, New York, 1965 (Folder 2)
  - Vishniakova-Akimova, V., "Two Years in China During the Insurrection, 1925-1927, Reminiscences," Moscow, 1965 (Folder 3)
  - Wolfe, Bertram D., "Backwardness and Industrialization in Russian History and Thought," reprint, Slavic Review, Vol. XXVI, No. 2, 1967 (Folder 4)
  - Zenkovsky, Serge, "A Century of Tatar Revival," reprint, The American Slavic and East European Review, Vol. XII, October 1953 (Folder 5)
- CARD FILE
  - "Civil War in South Russia, 1918-1921" (Box 44)
  - Comintern front organizations (Box 45)
  - World Peace Congresses and World Federation of Democratic Youth (Box 46)
  - Miscellaneous sources
  - Miscellaneous sources (Box 47)
  - Author and title index (Box 48)
  - Subject index